Joel Munsell Collection
Joel Munsell Collection
1861-1958
Bannister, Henry S.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American printer and antiquarian, founder of Albany, New York, firm which bore his name. Collection includes Munsell family genealogy, letter to William Leete Stone, letters about Munsell, invoices and receipts, photographic portraits, and biographer David S. Edelstein's research on the life and work of Joel Munsell.
149754
Biographical History
Joel Munsell (1808-1880) was an American printer and antiquarian, and the founder of the Albany, New York, firm which bore his name. He was particularly interested in the history and application of the art of printing; his extensive collection of works on that subject was in part purchased by the New York State Library.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Joel Munsell Collection, compiled by Henry S. Bannister, comprises the papers of Joel Munsell and other members of the Munsell family, along with David Edelstein's research files and notes relating to his biography of Munsell.
Joel Munsell papers include a family genealogy, Munsell's diary, correspondence, a manuscript of an essay, an item printed by Munsell for James B. Jermain, photographs, receipts, and miscellaneous material.
David Edelstein's files consist of sixteen correspondence and subject files relating to his research for and the publication of his book Joel Munsell: Printer and Antiquarian (Columbia University, 1950).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection as a whole is arranged in alphabetical order; within that, correspondence is in chronological order. David Edelstein's files may be found at the end of the collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Publishing, printing and book arts; New York State; Edelstein, David Simeon, 1913-; Edelstein, David Simeon, 1913- -- Joel Munsell: printer and antiquarian.; Munsell, Joel, 1808-1880.; Stone, William Leete, 1835-1908.; Joel Munsell's Sons.; Biographers -- United States.; Printers -- United States.; Printers -- New York (State) -- Albany.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- Albany.; Correspondence.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Genealogies (histories); Photographs.; Receipts (financial records); Research notes.; Biographers.; Printers.; Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Davis S. Edelstein files, gift of Davis S. Edelstein.
Inventory
- Joel Munsell papers
  - Genealogy of Munsell family, annotated (Box 1)
  - Joel Munsell's diary, 1848-1878; transcribed by Emma Munsell Hevenor (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1847-1886 (gaps) (Box 1)
    named correspondents are P. Canfield, James C. Wetmore, Frederick Morrison, Lt. James H. Clark, H. A. Houghton, J. Dimon, William Leete Stone (with picture of Munsell affixed to verso), and W. D. Haar; includes postcard from Munsell's Sons, Printers and Publishers
  - Manuscript, circa 1846 (Box 1)
    Essay written by Munsell for the New York Historical Society on the early history of printing in Albany; also copies of two letters about the article
  - Munsell imprint, 1873 (Box 1)
    "To the children and children's children and family friends of Mrs. Catherine Ann Jermain, this brief record is inscribed, at the wish of her husband. Christmas, 1873"; also includes Munsell's invoice to the publisher, James B. Jermain, and 5 associated invoices related to the printing of the work
  - Photographic portraits of Munsell, 1830; 1834,; 1870,; undated; 7 items (Box 1)
    Carte-de-visite (1870?) by S. J. Thompson, State St., Albany, with caption "aet. 62"
    Photograph of 1834 miniature painted on ivory
    Silver print, undated
    Albumen photograph portrait, undated
    Photograph of silhouette of Munsell, circa 1830
    Engraving of Munsell, inscribed "Yours truly, J. Munsell"
  - Receipts, bills (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    Deed of sale, Joseph Northrup of Hosick to Thomas Osborn of Hosick, $150 for six acres of land, dated 14 May 1810 and witnessed by Hez. [Hezekiah] Munsell
- David Edelstein files
  - American Antiquarian Society (Box 1)
  - Book reviews (Box 1)
  - Columbia University (Box 1)
  - Greenfield and Northfield, Massachusetts (Box 1)
  - Hevenor, Emma Munsell, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Hough, Franklin Benjamin (Box 1)
  - Muller, Harriet M. (Box 1)
  - Munsell family, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - New York State Library (Box 1)
  - Silver, Rollo (Box 1)
  - Warshaw collection (Box 1)
  - Individuals, A-Z (Box 1)
  - Institutions
    - Historical societies, A-Z (alphabetical by place) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, A-Z (Box 1)